## **MATTHEW DICK**

8650 29th Way N # 107 Pinellas Park, FL 33782 • 240-527-5762 • Matthew.Dick@outlook.com • linkedin.com/in/matt-dick

### INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY EXECUTIVE

Skilled IT leader with a successful history of directing multiple software development organizations, ensuring rapid adaptation to evolving business needs and driving revenue growth while reducing expenses across the organization. Utilizes technical expertise to drive technology vision, recommending and implementing critical systems and solutions. Effectively bridges the gap, making technical concepts and content understandable to non-technical audiences. Analyzes problems at a strategic and operational level and delivers resolutions that balance risks and benefits.

#### **SKILLS AND PROFICIENCIES**

- IT Management
- IT Strategy
- Project Management
- Budgeting
- Problem Solving
- Strategic Planning

- Team Building
- Leadership
- Project Delivery
- Agile
- Vendor Management
- JIRA

- Communication
- Waterfall PM
- Requirements
- React
- Javascript
- C#

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## First Data Corporation - Hagerstown, MD Manager / Director IT, 03/2007 - 04/2019

Lead application development and architecture for several teams coding in various languages such as DotNet, C#, ASP, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, SQL Server and Oracle to make web based applications and restful API's. The teams consisted of more than 80 people both domestic and off-shore. Each team had varying functional and development charters and programming skills utilized to implement comprehensive enterprise-wide technological strategies for various areas of the business. The applications across the various IT teams coded and supported the main help desk web application, merchant boarding and account creation, auth switch provisioning, hooks into credit, leasing and billing, consolidated multiple third party terminal download systems into a single ASP web application, as well all the warehouse deployment and reclamation processes which included key injection, terminal initial application downloading, automated pick to light for packing, merchant terminal shipping and tracking, reclamation for repairs and replacements. Maintain and balance a \$5.2 million budget that encompasses up to 50 projects at any one time.

 Designed and launched a single web interface to the various terminal download systems that normalized various configurations and settings resulting in a decrease in user training for multiple systems and streamlined the merchant boarding process.

- Pioneered a new communication protocol for the First Data proprietary terminal that allowed terminals to shorten the time for application loads as well as recovery logic if the data flow is interrupted, saving telecom expenses of \$4.1 million per year.
- Designed and implemented a universal boarding API allowing various systems to board new terminals via a single interface resulting in development savings for other systems.
- Invented and implemented a new rotating security feature for all downloads that resulted in over \$1.2 million savings per year in fraud.
- Led the internal implementation of various third-party terminal download systems, reducing licensing expenses by \$400K per year.
- Replaced the merchant equipment and terminal management system with a new Angular web interface and web services, allowing rapid deployment of new features without system outages.
- Implemented a new system monitoring solution that enhanced awareness of potential issues earlier thus avoiding production impacts resulting in less system outages.
- Delivered a solution to ensure all sensitive information is encrypted in the database while at rest and masked in the user interface. When sensitive information is unmasked, audit controls log the user that unmasked the information, resulting in a reduction in fraud.
- Designed the base flow for the First Data line of terminal products and helped stand up a new development team of 8 programmers to code credit, debit, and gift card applications, resulting in significant savings of third-party development expenses.
- Led the effort to code and implement over 6,000 credit card terminals into a single fast food chain resulting in revenue of approximately \$4.5 million for terminal hardware sales and recurring monthly processing revenue.

# First Data Corporation - Hagerstown, MD Senior Application Architect, 03/2002 – 02/2007

Lead two development teams for two separate systems with different coding skills and languages. Each of the teams supported important business systems and had different business initiatives. Led designs for all projects and development work and ensured that all projects were completed on time and within budget.

- Led the development and automation of various parts of off-host chargeback and retrieval systems and the association fulfillment processes, effectively reducing manual processes.
- Instrumental leader and decision maker for a large system integration and automation project due to a corporate merger. Successfully drove hardware cost savings and recurring IT development savings as well as the elimination of redundant manual processes.
- Created a VB application to track manual picking orders for a warehouse process, saving both labor and consumable expenses.

First Data Corporation - Hagerstown, MD Application Architect, 03/1996 - 02/2002

Lead the PC Help Desk team in response to issues with associates work stations.

- Created and lead the first PC hardware support team in the company resulting in faster resolution for user desktop issues resulting in less downtime.
- Developed a web-based ticket tracking system that prioritized the importance of issues to ensure fastest service possible.
- Implemented Unitech which automating the balancing of financials in the core process resulting in reduction of 10 people performing manual balancing processes.

### **EDUCATION AND MILITARY SERVICE**

Computer Science/Computer Information Systems Coursework, Hagerstown Community College US Navy Veteran with United States - Navy Suncoast Developers Guild - Full Stack Development (React, Javascript, C#)

### **ACTIVITIES AND HONORS**

Two time "Leader of the Pack" winner for outstanding performance.
Four-time BRAVO winner for being a key leader on various projects.
Past President and longtime member of Antietam Exchange Club
Past board member of the Parent Child center for the prevention of child abuse.
Past President and Vice-President of Washington County Black Rock Golf Course.